<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable discourse shewing the necessity of union amongst Protestants, in opposition to popery, as the only means (under God) to preserve the reformed religion also, the charge of persecution, lately maintained against the established religion, by W.P., H.C. and other insignificant scriblers, detected : proving it to be the ministers of state, and not the church, that prosecuted the penal laws on Protestant dissenters.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14748</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142619</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 778:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable discourse shewing the necessity of union amongst Protestants, in opposition to popery, as the only means (under God) to preserve the reformed religion also, the charge of persecution, lately maintained against the established religion, by W.P., H.C. and other insignificant scriblers, detected : proving it to be the ministers of state, and not the church, that prosecuted the penal laws on Protestant dissenters.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</term>
               <term>Cave, Henry.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98010:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98010:1"/>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe SHEWING The Neceſſity of UNION AMONGST PROTESTANTS In Oppoſition to POPERY, As the only Means (under God) to preſerve the Reformed Religion</p>
            <p>ALSO, The Charge of Perſecution, lately main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt the Eſtabliſhed Religion by <hi>W. P. H. C.</hi> and other <hi>Inſignificant</hi> Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, detected; Proving it to be the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>State,</hi> and not the <hi>Church,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proſecuted the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> on <hi>Proteſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRINTED in the Year, 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:98010:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98010:2"/>
            <p>THE known ſaying in the <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> That a <hi>Kingdom divided can't ſtand,</hi> is very ſeaſonable at this Juncture, by all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to be ſeriouſly conſidered: And if ever <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> (if not in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> yet in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi>) will be neceſſary, it muſt certainly be <hi>Now;</hi> when the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> is ſeeking, by all means imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to correct ſuch <hi>Diviſions</hi> amongſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as if poſſible to tender them irreconcileable <hi>One</hi> to the <hi>Other.</hi> And though the <hi>Differences</hi> are not extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; yet it has been the <hi>Polity</hi> of thoſe that delight in the <hi>Diviſion</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> (as they call them) to widen the <hi>Breaches,</hi> and, as much as poſſible, divide the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> To effect this <hi>Deſign,</hi> how often have we heard of the many <hi>Diſguiſes</hi> and <hi>Shapes</hi> they have appeared in, among all ſorts of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (none excepted); and it is lamentable to think, how great an effect they have had on <hi>Paſſionate Men,</hi> of all <hi>Perſwaſions.</hi> But now, conſidering the circumſtances of <hi>Things,</hi> and how darkly they appear to <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>diſcerning Eyes,</hi> it's high time for all <hi>Parties</hi> to lay aſide <hi>Pride, Paſſion,</hi> or <hi>Diviſion;</hi> and, as far as poſſible, agree to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Serve</hi> each <hi>Other.</hi> The doing of which, is the only effectual Means to eſtabliſh a laſting <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and to ſubvert the <hi>Deſigns</hi> of <hi>Plotting-Men,</hi> who would gladly over-turn our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws.</hi> The <hi>Conſiderations</hi> above-mentioned, cauſed me to give the beſt <hi>Advice</hi> I could: I muſt confeſs, not only my ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, but alſo my engagement in Buſineſs, very much prevented my <hi>Deſign:</hi> But however, what I here offer, comes from a ſincere <hi>Deſire</hi> for allaying the <hi>Heats,</hi> and uniting the <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in general. I hope, I ſhall not offer any think contrary to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Publick Good</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi> I ſhall begin with the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthy Sirs,</hi> The former <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> of ſome few <hi>Raſh Men</hi> amongſt you, together with their <hi>Zeal</hi> to ſerve an ungrateful ſort of <hi>Men,</hi> rendred almoſt the whole <hi>Body</hi> obnoxious to the hard <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Cenſure</hi> of many <hi>Worthy Men;</hi> inſomuch, that thoſe who were really <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as by <hi>Law</hi> eſtabliſh'd, were at a ſtand, and did not know what to think of the ſtrange and unaccountable <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of many, both <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laiety:</hi> But, as this Fault can be imputed to but a ſmall part of you, ſo I have that <hi>Charity</hi> to hope, they are, by this time, fully convinced of their <hi>Error,</hi> and will act more Prudently for the future. The heat of a few <hi>Raſh Men</hi> ought not to bring ſo Venerable a Body of Men into contempt; for by that Rule, the moſt <hi>Innocent</hi> would be lyable to anſwer for the moſt <hi>Guilty;</hi> the Injuſtice of which, can't be ſufficiently declared with Abhorrence.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98010:3"/>
            <p>My humble Advice is; As you have always manifeſted your <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> ſo continue Obedient <hi>Subjects,</hi> as far as the <hi>Laws of God</hi> and the <hi>Land,</hi> warrant your <hi>Obedience,</hi> and no farther are you actively obliged to <hi>Obey;</hi> (as to your <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> ye are no Strangers to the meaning of it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I wave it:) Let your <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human Laws,</hi> thereto agreeing, be without the leaſt Heſitation or Reluctancy: But, if any thing be commanded by <hi>Man,</hi> you muſt always remember your prime <hi>Obedience</hi> is due to <hi>God;</hi> and no <hi>Commands, Threats,</hi> or <hi>Allurements,</hi> ought to Influence you ſo, as to violate the <hi>Laws of God,</hi> or the <hi>Land;</hi> always have an Eye to the <hi>Divine,</hi> which infinitely ſupercedes any <hi>Command</hi> or <hi>Human Law.</hi> For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, if at any time you are required to renounce your <hi>Sence</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and believe <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or to <hi>Worſhip Images, Invocate Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> or any other thing, contrary to <hi>Scripture;</hi> or to change your Holy, Pure, and Sound <hi>Religion,</hi> to embrace another, abounding with <hi>Novelties,</hi> full of <hi>Human Inventions</hi> and <hi>Abſurdities;</hi> and that has little or no foundation on <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon:</hi> You are not, on any pretence whatſoever, to forſake your <hi>certain Religion,</hi> for the embracing of <hi>One,</hi> not only <hi>dubious</hi> but <hi>dangerous:</hi> And let me aſſure all wavering <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> (who, for Worldly <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Preferments,</hi> care not what <hi>Religion</hi> they are of) That they cannot Anſwer it to <hi>God,</hi> if they make Shipwrack of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by turning from a ſafe and rational <hi>Religion,</hi> to that which is not only <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> but very <hi>ridiculous,</hi> in the judgment of all Good <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Since the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is founded on <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> conſonant to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the practice of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> in all <hi>Ages;</hi> you, and all that deſire to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves ſincere <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ought to continue ſtedfaſt in that <hi>Divine Faith,</hi> you profeſs your ſelves <hi>Members</hi> of. If your <hi>Religion</hi> was built only on the <hi>Sandy Foundations</hi> of <hi>Tradition, Infallibility,</hi> &amp;c. you might have ſome tollerable <hi>Plea</hi> for altering your <hi>Opinion;</hi> but as long as your <hi>Religion</hi> teaches you <hi>Obedience</hi> in all Things to <hi>God,</hi> and likewiſe to your <hi>Soveraign,</hi> in which you have ſound Expoſitions of the <hi>Divine Truths,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments</hi> duly and truly adminiſtred in <hi>both kinds,</hi> according to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> no ways <hi>Lock'd up</hi> from <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laiety,</hi> (Becauſe all theſe, and what-ever more is neceſſary for the ordering of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>'s <hi>Converſation,</hi> is to be found in the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi>) I can't conceive, why any one ſhould change his <hi>Profeſſion. Worldly Intereſts, Troubles,</hi> or <hi>Temptations,</hi> ought to have no ſway or force with us, when they come in competition with our <hi>pure Religion.</hi> I have enlarged the more on this <hi>Head,</hi> by reaſon now is a time of greater tryal than formerly: and that ſome, who not long ſince eſteemed themſelves <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Faith,</hi> have now, for ſiniſter Ends, without <hi>Reaſon,</hi> departed from it. But let them ſeriouſly conſider, there is a <hi>God</hi> above, who will not be <hi>Mocked.</hi> Such <hi>unſtable Souls</hi> I ſhall leave to that <hi>God,</hi> who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98010:3"/>all Men, and rewardoth All according to their <hi>Deeds,</hi> whether <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, Let the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> be your <hi>Rule;</hi> Be ſure give no advantage to the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> either by a partial Execution of them, or by doing leſs than the <hi>Laws</hi> allow: neither ſtrain them too <hi>high,</hi> nor let them be as a <hi>Cypher,</hi> which will ſignifie nothing, without the <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Execution.</hi> As the publick Good and Welfare of <hi>Mankind,</hi> was the deſign of all <hi>Laws;</hi> ſo the Conformity to, and Execution of them, ought to have the ſame tendency. To ſtrain any <hi>Law</hi> beyond the deſigned <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Intent</hi> of the <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> is a moſt ſevere and unjuſt <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> and to <hi>ſuſpend,</hi> or let wholeſome and beneficial <hi>Laws</hi> lye <hi>dormant,</hi> without all due Execution for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> does not only ſhew the unfaithfulneſs of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> to whom the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive Power</hi> appertains; but alſo, how little he minds his <hi>Sworn Duty,</hi> which is to ſee the <hi>Laws</hi> duly put in <hi>Execution;</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> according to them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually diſtributed without <hi>Partiality;</hi> and how any can Anſwer the <hi>nullifying</hi> them, without a Lawful <hi>Abrogation,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Power</hi> that <hi>Enacted</hi> them, I can't poſſibly conceive; for the common approved Maxim is, <hi>That Power only that made any</hi> Law, <hi>has ſufficient Authority to ſuſpend or repeal the ſame.</hi> The Laws of the <hi>Land,</hi> ſo long as they are founded on <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and found beneficial to the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ought to be kept Inviolable, and maintain'd by All; but more eſpecially by thoſe that have any ſhare in the <hi>Execution</hi> of them. We ſhould reckon him a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> that ſhould <hi>un-tile</hi> his Houſe, under pretence of keeping out the <hi>Rain.</hi> Likewiſe, if a Governour of a well Fortified City, who wanted for no Accommodations requiſite for the defence of it, ſhould, without any juſt cauſe of Fear of his Inconſiderable Enemies, either out of <hi>Cowardice</hi> or <hi>Perfidiouſneſs,</hi> betray the City, and make himſelf and them, not only void of <hi>Power,</hi> but in effect <hi>Slaves</hi> to the Will and Pleaſures of that part of Men, to whom he and they might have bid defiance. What can we ſay or think of ſuch <hi>Eſau's,</hi> that are ready to ſell their <hi>Birth Rights</hi> for a <hi>Meſs</hi> of <hi>Pottage,</hi> but that they ſhall not deſerve any <hi>Compaſſion?</hi> and if they undergo the greateſt <hi>Evils,</hi> they will have the juſt <hi>Reward</hi> they have deſervedly Merited. I ſhould not pity any Man, that, under pretence of keeping out <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> ſhould open the <hi>Door,</hi> and let them in; wholly truſting to their good <hi>Breeding, Kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty;</hi> not in the leaſt believing they would be ſo <hi>unmannerly,</hi> as not only to ſecure him, by binding his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> that he could not help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but alſo Rob him of all that was worth their carrying away; ſtopping his <hi>Mouth</hi> that he could not complain of his hard <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> or call for any help, to free him out of his miſerable <hi>Condition.</hi> I wiſh, in the Land of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> there were not too many, that would ſhew the ſame kindneſs to thoſe kind Hearted <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that ſhould diveſt themſelves of the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Security</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98010:4"/>the <hi>Law</hi> gives them, and meerly truſt to their good <hi>Nature,</hi> for their <hi>Religion,</hi> and all their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties.</hi> Any Man, with whom the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Juſtice</hi> is Intruſted, or that has the Honour to be Elected a Member of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the Service of his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> for ſuch a Man to betray his <hi>Truſt,</hi> either by <hi>parting</hi> with thoſe <hi>wholſome Laws,</hi> that long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience tells us, are abſolutely neceſſary, and moſt beneficial to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth;</hi> or by condeſcending to the unreaſonable <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Endeavours</hi> of an inconſiderable ſort of Men; or by not <hi>obſtructing,</hi> but <hi>conſenting</hi> to the Enacting of <hi>New Laws,</hi> deſtructive to the <hi>Common Good;</hi> He is moſt unworthy of the <hi>Truſt</hi> repoſed in him, and deſerves the ſevereſt <hi>Puniſhment</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> will admit of: No <hi>Contempt, Diſgrace,</hi> or <hi>Deriſion,</hi> can be bad enough for ſuch a Man, that to ſerve his own particular private <hi>Intereſt,</hi> will <hi>Sacrifice</hi> the <hi>Publick.</hi> All <hi>Members of Parliament,</hi> when they deſign to make any <hi>Laws,</hi> ought throughly to conſider, what <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Benefit</hi> will accrue to the <hi>Subjects</hi> thereby; and if, upon mature Conſideration, they ſee a neceſſity of Enacting ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> by no means ought they to be <hi>omitted,</hi> or <hi>laid aſide.</hi> On the other ſide, if former <hi>Parliaments</hi> had, for weighty <hi>Reaſons,</hi> made ſeveral <hi>Acts</hi> for the ſecurity of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws;</hi> before theſe <hi>Laws</hi> be made void by a <hi>Repeal,</hi> due reſpect ought to be had to the circumſtances of <hi>Things</hi> and <hi>Times;</hi> and, after a ſtrict and impartial Enquiry be made, if it ſhall appear that the Repealing thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> will not only very much <hi>injure,</hi> but really <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger</hi> the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> then, notwithſtanding the Solicitations of a <hi>Party,</hi> whoſe <hi>Intereſts</hi> oblige them to deſire it, they ought not to part with <hi>Laws</hi> which will prove as an <hi>impregnable Bulwark</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Enemies.</hi> To make void an uſeful and neceſſary <hi>Law,</hi> under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of doing <hi>Good</hi> to the <hi>Publick</hi> thereby, is like the taking up of a <hi>Sluce</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> an <hi>Inundation of Water.</hi> I may rather compare it to the throwing of <hi>Combuſtible Matter</hi> into an Houſe on <hi>Fire,</hi> thinking thereby to <hi>Extinguiſh the Flames;</hi> which is ſo far from putting a period to them, that, on the contrary, it heightens the <hi>Flames,</hi> that they are not (if at all) eaſily Maſtered. I have heard our neceſſary <hi>Laws</hi> compared to the moſt uſeful <hi>Damms</hi> and <hi>Banks</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> to prevent the raging <hi>Sea</hi> from over-whelming them. It's well known to <hi>Travellers,</hi> of what a vaſt Importance thoſe <hi>Defences</hi> are: for, ſhould there be a conſiderable Breach made in any of thoſe <hi>Damms,</hi> that ſecure them from the violence of the <hi>Water;</hi> not only many <hi>Souls, Beaſts,</hi> and many other <hi>valuable Things</hi> would be loſt; but it would be an Immenſe Charge to repair them: But, though the damage to the <hi>Netherlands</hi> would be very great, ſhould ſuch a bad accident happen; yet it's the Opinion of <hi>Wiſe men,</hi> (and not without good grounds) that ſhould <hi>Engliſh-Men</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> part with thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> that are like a <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>impregnable Defence</hi> to them, and their <hi>Religion,</hi> in <hi>one Reſpect</hi> it would be of a far worſe conſequence to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98010:4"/>them; that is, the <hi>loſe</hi> would be <hi>irrepairable;</hi> and <hi>Ten Thouſand</hi> to <hi>One,</hi> if ever the like <hi>Security</hi> can be obtain'd. <hi>Country-men</hi> have an <hi>Old,</hi> but <hi>True ſaying;</hi> that is, <hi>If you love to be free from a Broken Head, keep faſt the Staff in your own hand;</hi> ſo may you not only prevent your being <hi>beaten</hi> by your <hi>own Weapon,</hi> but, in caſe of an <hi>Aſſault,</hi> you may, by being in a poſture of <hi>Defence,</hi> eaſily defend your ſelf from <hi>violent Hands;</hi> whereas on the contrary, a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Man</hi> may eaſily be <hi>Captivated;</hi> and, whether he will or no, he will be conſtrain'd to ſubmit to the <hi>Mercy</hi> of his <hi>Inſulting Enemy.</hi> It's farther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That after the <hi>Rich Farmer</hi> has, with much difficulty, gotten a good <hi>Eſtate,</hi> he remembers how hardly he <hi>Laboured, Toiled,</hi> and <hi>Sweated,</hi> before he brought things to ſo good an <hi>Iſſue;</hi> and the calling to mind his former Indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Labour, has this effect on him, That ſince he obtain'd his <hi>Riches</hi> or <hi>Subſtance</hi> with no ſmall <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Induſtry,</hi> he is reſolved, becauſe he neither got it eaſily, nor can he diſpence with the want of it, that he will not do like <hi>Prodigal Sons,</hi> who being Born to their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and wholly Ignorant of their Parents <hi>Care and Trouble</hi> to provide for them, quickly ſquander away vaſt <hi>Fortunes:</hi> but though he may love his Children or Friends with all the real Affections imaginable; yet, ſays he, <hi>Charity begins at home; I muſt not make my ſelf a Beggar, and ſtand to the Courteſie of Children or Friends, for what I ſhall want to ſuſtain me, ſo that I may comfortably end thoſe days that remain.</hi> For woful Experience too frequently informs us, <hi>That Children and Friends too ſoon forget their Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and the innumerable Kindneſſes of their tender Parents.</hi> Since things are thus, let common Prudence dictate better things to us, than to part with what of right belongs unto us, or to let go that <hi>lawful Security</hi> we have, for all that is dear unto us; and by ſo doing, we may eaſily prevent our being made a Prey to our implacable <hi>Enemies,</hi> from whoſe tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> I might much more enlarge on this particular but, ſhould I proceed to enumerate all the manifeſt <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies</hi> that I could eaſily inſiſt on, I ſhould cry out with the <hi>Poet, Tantae molis erat Romanam condere gente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, Let your Zeal for your Holy Religion continue, and let your <hi>Moderation</hi> be ſeen by your very <hi>Enemies;</hi> and let not the worſt of them, have any juſt cauſe of laying any <hi>ſevere</hi> or <hi>unbecoming Actions</hi> to your charge. How will it pleaſe your <hi>Enemies,</hi> to ſee you <hi>differing</hi> and <hi>dividing</hi> your <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> with thoſe? That a Worthy, and moſt Learned Member of your Church, in my hearing; lately Preach'd againſt excluding by <hi>Excommunication,</hi> from <hi>Communion</hi> with you, for <hi>indifferent Things,</hi> which may be left, <hi>undone,</hi> and yet <hi>Salvation</hi> obtained. The reaſons he gave for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them were, Becauſe there were <hi>many good Chriſtians among them;</hi> and becauſe they <hi>proteſted againſt the ſame Errors, believed the ſame Articles of Faith, and hoped for the ſame common Salvation by Chriſt, that you do.</hi> You
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98010:5"/>can't but be deeply ſenſible, how many Eyes are fixed on you, and what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires your <hi>Enemies</hi> have of ſeeing you expoſed to <hi>Publick Shame</hi> and <hi>Contempt:</hi> Have <hi>Charity</hi> towards all Men, eſpecially to all thoſe of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that in any tollerable Meaſure conform to the Rules of it. As for your <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Neighbours,</hi> (like the Reverend Doctors, <hi>Till.</hi> and <hi>Ten.</hi>) let your Love and Moderation be ſo great towards them, as if poſſible, though you cannot make them ſatisfied with your Reaſons for <hi>Conformity;</hi> yet let your <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to them as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of the ſame Body you profeſs to be, have ſuch an Influence over them, as to expel any Malice or prejudice they might have entertain'd againſt your Perſons; and who knows, but ſuch Methods as theſe, may have a great Influence towards a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conformity. It's my Opinion, (and not without Reaſon) That the bitter <hi>Invectives</hi> not long ſince, in and out of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> created greater and fiercer Enemies againſt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> than otherwiſe ſhe would have had; but as this has ſometime ſince ceaſed, ſo <hi>Charity</hi> ought to be exerciſed, in forgeting what was amiſs; in hopes the like may never be heard again.</p>
            <p>My Advice to you <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants,</hi> is, for the moſt part, the ſame I gave to the <hi>Church of England:</hi> I need not enlarge any farther on the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at this Seaſon, when it is very manifeſt, that nothing is more delightful or acceptable to thoſe that have the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> than to ſee one <hi>Proteſtant</hi> rending, tearing, and back-biting another: It being too apparent, that theſe <hi>Fiſhers of Men</hi> delight in <hi>troubled Waters,</hi> knowing it to be the fitteſt time and opportunity to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their <hi>Heretical Enemies,</hi> (for ſo they call <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) when their Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among themſelves are greateſt. Therefore, I earneſtly perſwade and entreat you, as you tender the Peace and Welfare of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and the eſtabliſhing your ſound <hi>Religion,</hi> to put on a Spirit of <hi>Meekneſs, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Complyance,</hi> as far as poſſible, with the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and if you can't receive ſatisfaction enough from her Learned Members, throughly to <hi>Conform;</hi> yet let not your <hi>Charity</hi> be ſo narrow, as to have a bad Opinion of thoſe Worthy Men, that are abundantly ſatisfied with the reaſonableneſs of their <hi>Conformity.</hi> As you deſire no harſh Cenſures be paſt on you for <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> ſo be ſure you avoid reflecting on thoſe Pious Men, that hold it lawful to aſſent and conſent to all the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> If poſſible, have Peace with all Men, eſpecially with thoſe of the ſame Houſhold of <hi>Faith</hi> you profeſs. Strongly endeavour to prevent bitter <hi>Invective Speeches</hi> againſt that Church; which, in all probability, is like to be the only Invincible <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark</hi> againſt <hi>Popery:</hi> And I am the more inclin'd to be an earneſt Advocate for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> nor only becauſe I have hopes ſhe has laid aſide thoſe bitter Things, formerly, with ſome Truth, laid to her charge; but chiefly becauſe a vaſt number of her Worthy, and eminently Learned Members,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98010:5"/>have, with great Learning and Solidity defended our Holy Religion, from the <hi>Hereſie, Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Novelty</hi> falſly charged on it by the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> All Perſons that Study any thing to the purpoſe, of the Controverſie betwixt us and them, muſt certainly perceive, how admirably they have confuted the unreaſonable and unaccountable Doctrines of that pretended Infallible <hi>Church;</hi> clearly proving the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and that we are not (as they pretend) beholding to them for it: But evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently making it appear, that the <hi>Proteſtant Faith</hi> is moſt ancient, and that its Doctrine is conſonant or agreeable to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the practice of the <hi>pureſt Chriſtians,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Times.</hi> This very conſideration alone, is ſufficient to clear the Body of that Church from being <hi>Popiſhly affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Reaſon to Love and Eſteem them for, is, their firm adhering to the known <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land; for what-ever a few unfound <hi>Members</hi> of her <hi>Communion</hi> have done to the contrary, yet ſhe is not accountable for them; the greateſt and moſt conſiderable part, having been found very faithful on that account.</p>
            <p>A third Thing, for which you ought to value the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> viz. Their ſtedfaſt adhering to the Rights of the <hi>People,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the <hi>Clergy.</hi> Their <hi>Conſciences</hi> have been ſo juſt, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Angry Frowns of Majeſty have taken hold of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and that they have, and are likely to ſuffer very much by it; they rather chooſe to truſt <hi>God</hi> with their Temporal Felicity and Comfort, than ſinfully violate thoſe Sacred Oaths they have ſo Solemnly taken, by betraying (in the leaſt) the Truſt repoſed in them; notwithſtanding the Frowns or Allurements of the greateſt Men. This only ſingle Inſtance of their ſignal Fidelity to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> ought to have no ſmall ſway or Influence with all conſidering Perſons. He that orders his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation according to the Divine Rule, and faithfully Studies to preſerve the juſt <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Lawful Liberties</hi> of Mankind, deſervedly Merits the greateſt Love and Affection imaginable. But he that makes no Conſcience of his Duty to <hi>God,</hi> and deſignedly makes Ship-wrack of the Lawful Rights and Priviledges of any <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Society,</hi> and that will Sell his Birth-Right for an inconſiderable Value, deſerves not the Name of a Man, or to be admitted into the Society of Mankind. I deſire you would imitate the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in all thoſe things for which I juſtly commend her. In the firſt place, Follow her Loyalty as far as you can, and not break the Laws of <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Men,</hi> thereto correſponding. In the ſecond place, Be ſervent and conſtant in the Sacred <hi>Religion</hi> you profeſs your ſelves Members of. You know, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, the greateſt part of you, the Tranſcendent Excellency of your <hi>Religion;</hi> and therefore, if any of you ſhould, for Intereſt or Preferment, turn from <hi>Truth</hi> to <hi>Falſhood,</hi> from <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Darkneſs</hi> from a <hi>Sound</hi> to a <hi>Corrupt Religion;</hi> How great and unpardonable would ſo wilful a Sin be? And, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98010:6"/>ſpeak the Truth, I muſt do you the Juſtice to commend you for your firmneſs in your Holy Profeſſion, in that I have heard few or none, that have either gone over, or been perverted to the Communion of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the alluring Favours of that Church towards you, and practice of her <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laiety</hi> to gain Proſelytes among you. What I ſhall ſay on this Head, is, <hi>Go on, and Proſper;</hi> and, without doubt, the Spirit of Truth will guide and direct you for the beſt. In the third place, Imitate their Fidelity to the Laws of the Land: You can't, but with admiration, perceive how ſtedfaſtly they labour to preſerve them, and all the reaſonable Rights and Priviledges of the People. As you are Rational Men, profeſſing the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and render the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> let not any uncertain Tranſitory Intereſt prevail with you ſo far, as baſely to give up your <hi>Religion,</hi> and the known uſeful <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, be ſure, you neither conſent to the ſuſpending, or taking away any, that (to all Intelligent Men) are like to prove your only Security. When the <hi>Country-man</hi> deſigns to preſerve his <hi>Grain,</hi> from thoſe Creatures that would Eat it up, or otherwiſe ſpoil it, he is far from rooting up the Fence that ſecures it: So ought you carefully to preſerve the Laws, for your own and the Publick Safety. Things at preſent look, to you perhaps, with a good Aſpect; I wiſh, they may long continue in that condition: But, if the courſe of things ſhould mightily alter, and theſe <hi>Halcion Days</hi> (of which you have no aſſurance) ſhould not long continue, how greatly would your hopeful expectations be fruſtrated? Therefore, be ſure you do not impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently purchaſe your preſent Liberty, and ſeeming Favours, at too dear a rate; for ſuch Acts may wholly deprive you of the Favours, that you may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe expect from the next Succeſſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſtrenuouſly endeavour to manifeſt to the World, that your former great out cries againſt the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of your <hi>Religion, Liberties, Properties,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, were really in earneſt and, that as then you truly hated thoſe that were in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure guilty of them; ſo now, it ſomething lyes in your Power, you will not by the greateſt Perſwaſions and Promiſes of Kindneſſes, be wrought on, to part with the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land becauſe you can't well be Ignorant of the fatal conſequence of ſo doing. If you either give us the Laws, or ceaſe to execute thoſe that are moſt neceſſary, you not only highly ſerve and gratifie your known <hi>Enemies;</hi> but by betraying your <hi>Truſt</hi> you will render your ſelves extraordinary Odiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Opinion of moſt Men; in that you are unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to what you formerly ſo much cryed up, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Laws</hi> might flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and <hi>Juſtice</hi> might duly and impartially be diſtributed, and all Men, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly poſſeſs what of right belongs to them. No Honeſt <hi>Man,</hi> or good <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> will diſſwade you from Serving or Obeying your Soveraign, as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lawful: But, in all Obedience, ſtrict recourſe muſt be had to the Divine and Human <hi>Laws,</hi> that the Limits of neither be Tranſgreſſed; and then the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98010:6"/>Iſſue of ſuch Obedience, will be of no ill conſequence to you or the Publick; Such Obedience will redound to your Immortal Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider, if the the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were not of a rigid, violent, and ambitious Nature, they would not make all this ſtir about the <hi>Teſt,</hi> which debars them from a ſhare in the Government. In <hi>Holland</hi> we know, that though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are very Peaceable, and have given many Years Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their good Behaviour, under a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Power; yet the <hi>States,</hi> for their own and the Publick Safety, will admit none of them into any <hi>Offices.</hi> I am of Opinion, and not without Reaſon, <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> here, can't give ſo good an account of their Peaceable and Chriſtian Behaviour, as thoſe in <hi>Holland</hi> can: Therefore, greater Arguments may be produced, why no Power ought to be granted to them in <hi>England:</hi> It being notoriouſly known, that though their Prince be a Juſt Man, valluing his Word, yet a reſtleſs Zeal moves the <hi>Papiſts (manibus pedibuſque)</hi> to advance what they call <hi>Catholick Intereſt;</hi> which, without any Reſtraint, will not keep within the bounds of Moderation.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Laws</hi> are taken off, I know not of any Obſtruction they can meet with; then we muſt expect to be <hi>Govern'd wholly by Papiſts,</hi> and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſuch a Government muſt be terrible to <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> for what can they expect leſs than <hi>Popiſh Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and from ſuch a <hi>Parliament,</hi> what leſs than a perfect eſtabliſhing of <hi>Popery</hi> by a <hi>Law;</hi> and, without doubt, when ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> are Enacted in favour of that <hi>Religion,</hi> as ſevere will be made againſt the <hi>growing of Proteſtant Hereſie</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> from ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Times, God</hi> in Mercy deliver <hi>England.</hi> Pray, therefore, conſider, if you once give the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſo much Power, whether, ſo ſoon as they have it, they will not make ſeverer <hi>Teſts</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> than ever were made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Church of Rome?</hi> The late Famous Actions of the <hi>French</hi> King, and the <hi>Marian</hi> Kindneſs of old, to <hi>Hereticks,</hi> are convincing Evidences of the Lenity and Moderation of a Government, wholly in the hands of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> As for the Happineſs, and flouriſhing of Kingdoms or Republicks, under the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> See the contrary in Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Travels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romaniſt</hi>'s great Ambition, and eager deſire to be in Eminent Places of Truſt, is enough to convince any Rational Man, that for no mean or inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Enterpriſes, do they contend for them: They think if once they can get into the <hi>Saddle,</hi> with greater eaſe they may Ride the poor <hi>Hereticks.</hi> I would adviſe you to Ponder, with great deliberation, the <hi>Natures, Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of thoſe Men, that with might and main la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to take off the <hi>Teſt.</hi> And if it ſhall appear, (as doubtleſs it will) 'tis a grievance to thoſe only, that eſpouſe a Forreign Intereſt, directly contrary to yours; and that the <hi>Teſt</hi> is a ſtrong defence to preſerve you. I hope you will manifeſt your real Love and Kindneſs to this Nation, by undergoing, for a time, as great Severities as ever, rather than in any degree be Inſtrumental
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98010:7"/>in ruining of this now happy Kingdom (I mean in her <hi>Laws</hi>). I would gladly know of any ambitious <hi>Papiſt,</hi> Whether it would not be more unreaſonably bold for him to deſire a ſhare in that Government, from which he is Legally excluded, than for a <hi>Hugonet</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where, as I never heard, were any <hi>Laws</hi> to exclude him, to deſire to be prefer'd to no ſmall Offices: I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily perſwaded the Body of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> there, would be very unwilling to be Govern'd by him; I think the caſe is not parrellel, and that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ought to inſiſt much more on the ſame Priviledge in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Fifth</hi> place, Seriouſly think of the profeſſed Kindneſs of your new Friends of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> you may and ought to conſider, <hi>Cui bono, For what good or deſign,</hi> is ſo great Friendſhip pretended, and ſo many Favours now on a ſuddain confer'd and accumulated on you; who, not long ſince, were eſteemed unwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hy of Life: You may well enquire, what occaſioned ſo great a <hi>Calm,</hi> after ſo violent and <hi>Tempeſtuous a Storm.</hi> It muſt, certainly, be matter of the higheſt admitation to you, to ſee the wonderful Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Clemency of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> at this time to you obſtinate <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks;</hi> eſpecially ſince the Members of that <hi>Church</hi> are now in ſo great Power: I ſay, to ſee a <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe Principles are directly oppoſite to the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> ſo careſs the <hi>ſtricteſt ſort of them;</hi> when as, not long ſince, the greateſt Violence and Cruelty imaginable, to extirpate them, was thought not only lawful, but neceſſary; it's well if you find theſe Kindneſſes real, and not to make you, what you hate to be, <hi>Tools</hi> for a Deſign both dangerous and diſhonourable: To ſee Men, one while, breath out nothing but <hi>Invectives</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Reformed;</hi> at another time, if it more ſerves their purpoſes, fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and courting <hi>Hereticks,</hi> is enough to put conſidering Men on their Guard. Such unexpected Kindneſſes may put you on enquiry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether you come nearer in Belief or Practice to that <hi>Church</hi> now? or, whether you be as guilty of <hi>Hereſie</hi> (as ſhe calls it) as ever?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether the uſual Spirit of Perſecution, and Antipathy to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> (though at preſent in <hi>England</hi> reſtrain'd) be not as predominant in <hi>France,</hi> and other places, as ever? It's well if <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> can Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their known and beloved Principles, in puting on a Moderation and Temper ſuitable to the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> If it be clearly evinced, that <hi>Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> have not in the leaſt obliged the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> by their receeding or depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their own Principles; or by their favourable conſtruction of the Articles and Opinions of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> then it is viſible their deſigns are (ſince the <hi>Church of England</hi> will not ſerve their turn) if poſſible, to make the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> their <hi>Tools,</hi> they being the laſt Refuge they can fly to, in order to their Aſſiſtance. The late Actions of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> towards you, beſpeak your favourable Opinion: But the too well known Maxim amongſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, That Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> doth juſtly cauſe <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98010:7"/>to expect no real or greater Kindneſſes from them, than conſiſts with their <hi>Intereſts</hi> or <hi>Deſigns</hi> to manifeſt. If the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhew you outwardly great Reſpect; and, for Siniſter Ends, treat you as Friends for a while, till you have ſerved their turn, by taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> that they might be on as equal Terms as you: It's not only <hi>Mine,</hi> but the Opinion of <hi>Ten Thouſand</hi> more; that not only you, but the Nation will dearly pay for the Kindneſſes you have received from them: And, let me tell you, if things are ſo ordered, you may Whiſtle for any place of Truſt in the <hi>Government:</hi> And when all the Adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice</hi> is wholly in the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (as doubtleſs then it will be) you <hi>Hereticks</hi> muſt be content with ſuch as can be got: For I know not where you can expect any Redreſs, or to whom you can appeal. Theſe Conſiderations, I hope, will make you perceive as great a neceſſity of continuing thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> as ever there were of Enacting them: eſpecially the <hi>Teſt.</hi> Pray <hi>God</hi> direct you, that you may act Prudently, for your own Credit, and the Nations Good. I have great cauſe to hope well of you, becauſe, for the moſt part, you are Men of Conſideration and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that ſcorn to be Acceſſaries, much leſs the chief Actors, in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the happy Conſtitution of our Government.</p>
            <p>I make no queſtion but your w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Carriage, at this time, by being faithful to your <hi>King,</hi> your <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Laws,</hi> will ſo far reconcile you to the favour of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that when ever a ſeaſonable Opportunity ſhall offer for the eaſing of you in a Legal way, her Members, will readily conſent to it; for they will not be ſo void of all Gratitude, as wholly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your ſumneſs to your Religion, and the neceſſary Laws of the Land; but if you Act contrary to the Intereſt of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and of the Nation, you can expect only the ſhort Favours of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> and not eaſily to be admitted into the favourable Opinion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe Kindneſſes from her, which otherwiſe you might expect. And I muſt profeſs, you will deſerve none of her Favours, if you ſtudy more to ſerve the <hi>Roman,</hi> than the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt:</hi> But I hope better things of you.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not enlarge, having (I hope) writ enough to have convinc'd you already. I ſhall Anſwer one grand <hi>Objection,</hi> relating to the <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> The <hi>Teſt</hi> (as I can underſtand) being not much Inſiſted on; unleſs by ſome Mercenary Men, whoſe Writings are all they have to depend on. The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Argument, for a preſent Repeal, with ſome timerous and paſſionate <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is this, That the Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> are of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Spirit; and as one, the other end of the City, ſaid, <hi>That while theſe Rods</hi> (meaning the <hi>Penal Laws</hi>) <hi>are in their hands, they will be continually laſhing</hi> Proteſtants: Therefore, it is (as he ſaid) the higheſt piece of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to take them off, while it is in their Power. I always heard a great account of the Gentleman, that his Memory was very good, his Parts very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98010:8"/>eminent: If ſo, I can't but admire he forgets, or at leaſt underſtands not, from whence thoſe ſevere Orders, for ruining <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> came: Nay, farther, for what Ends and Deſigns things were ſo violently carried on. Perhaps it may farther be Objected, That many of the Divines of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> often Zealouſly preſſed this Perſecution. I'll grant the Accuſation in part; but I can the better excuſe thoſe hot Men, when I conſider what <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, Incentives, and Promotions came from that end of the City, that now ſo much condemns the Church of</hi> England <hi>for her Zeal to Serve the King in that particular:</hi> Since things were ſo carried, that no <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> were eſteemed or preferred unleſs he would comply with <hi>Courtly Orders,</hi> in <hi>Thundring</hi> againſt <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> As there are, amongſt Men of all Perſwaſions, Ambitious, Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Men; ſo, I confeſs, there were ſome few ſuch as Mr. <hi>Thompſon</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> among the <hi>Church of England</hi> Divines: But for the Richer and more Learned part of that vaſt Body, I am fully convinc'd, few, if any, were of that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Spirit. Farther, The Worthy Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are grateful Underſtanding Men; and I have that Charity for them, as not to imagine, That if the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> be, to their Power, Friendly and Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Church of <hi>England</hi> now; if it ſhould ever lye in her Members Power hereafter, but that a trebble return of Kindneſs and Gratitude would by them be made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To conclude, I muſt profeſs, that I hate a Perſecuting Spirit in Men, pretending to Chriſtianity; and I do freely declare, I ſhould heartily rejoyce, if this time were a fit opportunity to relieve the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> but, were I in their condition, as I had already undergone much, ſo, by the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>God,</hi> I would Suffer much more, rather than, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who, when he had loſt part of his Strength, for Revenge, with what he had left, pull'd down the Houſe, not only on the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> but on his own Head. Such a Fooliſh Revenge would be but a poor ſatisfaction to a Rational Man: How aptly the compariſon is made, I leave to underſtanding <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to conſider.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98010:8"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Had almoſt forgot Two weighty Conſiderations; The firſt is, You ought to conſider, and ſeriouſly reflect on Courtly Favours and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and how the Court oppoſed the Kindneſſes deſign'd for you by the <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Parliament: I muſt acquaint you, That Three Parts in Four, of that Parliament, were ſtrict <hi>Church of England-Men;</hi> and that they had ſuch a reſpect for you, that they unanimouſly paſſed a <hi>Bill</hi> for eaſing of <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters;</hi> And I can't conceive, why it was by the Court obſtructed, unleſs becauſe it did not extend to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as well as <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters:</hi> However, for Reaſons beſt known to themſelves, inſtead of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the <hi>Bill</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to have his Royal Stamp, it was loſt (a thing never heard of before): This Act will ſufficiently clear the major part of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> from that Odious Accuſation of being Promoters of that Perſecution, then ſo vigorouſly carried on: And ſince it clears them, it muſt fall heavy ſomewhere: I do not affirm, the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> had any hand in loſing that <hi>Bill;</hi> but I know not what to think of it. No Man can doubt, but that great Kindneſs to <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> was really by that Parliament deſigned: But there was a conſiderable Party then in being, with whoſe Intereſts, Deſigns, and Glory, ſuch Lenity could not then conſiſt, what ever it may do now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Some great Advocates for Repealing the <hi>Teſt,</hi> pretend to an Expedient for it; and declare, they will part with it, provided ſuch Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as can be propoſed, may be gotten: As an Expedients, in another Caſe, was thought Odious and Ridiculous; ſo now, a <hi>Nominal,</hi> and not a <hi>Virtual</hi> Obligatory Law, ought to have the ſame Fate. It's my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, If the pretended Expedient be as Valid and Secure to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> as the <hi>Teſt,</hi> it would be equally indifferent for the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to let you keep what you have: And ſome think, if you muſt have a <hi>Teſt,</hi> it will not be grateful to the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> Wherein lyeth the Kindneſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98010:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the King, if he parts with any Law, and at the ſame time grants ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſevere, to Exclude his Subjects, (whom He thinks Worthy) from all publick Places of <hi>Truſt.</hi> I muſt freely tell you my Mind, If you are concern'd for preſerving your Religion, and what is dear to you, and us All, Remember, and abide by that common Proverb, <hi>One Bird in Hand, is worth Two in the Buſh.</hi> You would reckon a Purchaſer (though he were ſure of a Penniworth) very imprudent, if he ſhould Pay the full Value for his Land, before he were ſure to receive a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Title from the Vender. As to the Promoters and Patriots of an Expedient, in lieu of the <hi>Teſt,</hi> In the firſt place, are they ſure ſuch a thing will be granted? I put the <hi>Quaery,</hi> becauſe, if I am not miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the <hi>Draconical</hi> Author had no Thanks for propoſing it, in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the <hi>Letter to a Diſſenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, I ſhall give you my Sentiments in a plain Intelligible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: I can as ſoon be wrought upon to believe an Ignorant Pretender, that ſhall pretend to take out my Sound Teeth, and put in a better Sett in the room of them, as to Credit the Promoters of an Expedient: As I ſhould admire at the Confidence of the former, ſo I ſhould be amazed at the Ignorance of the latter. I believe the impoſſibility of my getting new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Teeth, and their getting as firm Security for the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> in place of the <hi>Teſt,</hi> will be alike equal: Therefore, be Prudent, and conſider the danger of altering a well-Eſtabliſh'd Government: For, it's manifeſt, when things are in Confuſion, it's a hard matter to ſet them right again.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
